<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="phonebook">
	<title>Phonebook - a typical Spring Web Flow application</title>
	<sect1>
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>
			This chapter explains some of the basic concepts of Spring Web Flow
			to you, using the Phonebook sample application distributed with the
			Spring Web Flow release. The phonebook application incorporates
			one of the most often found flows in web applications; i.e. the
			<emphasis>search + master/detail flow</emphasis>. In the next couple of
			sections, we will explain how to build that flow using Spring Web Flow.
			Let's first discuss a good process for building flows into your
			web application:
		</para>
		<para>
			<orderedlist spacing="compact">
				<listitem>
					<para>The first step in the process of adding a flow to your
					application is to actually <emphasis>design</emphasis> the flow.
					Storyboarding the flow helps here with simple sketches (and/or)
					a state diagram</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>The next step is to <emphasis>create the configuration for
					the Flow</emphasis>. The configuration should reflect the flow you've
					previously drawn on paper for example.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>After you've created the configuration for the flow, it's time
					to <emphasis>test the execution</emphasis> of the flow. This can be done using implementations
					of actions that haven't been fully completed yet.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>After you've ensured the flow executes correctly, you can
					implement the logic encapsulated in your flow by <emphasis>completing the
					action classes</emphasis> you've added to your flow configuration.
					In other words: the Action classes are <emphasis>the</emphasis> place
					where you can implement logic and somewhat resembles Spring MVC controllers
					(in fact, they can be Spring MVC controllers or action-like artifacts
					from any other MVC framework).</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>The last thing you need to do before you can deploy your flow is
					to <emphasis>implement the views</emphasis> for your flow. The views
					are the individual pages presented to the user. So remember:
					the views are the places where users are allowed to interact with the flow.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Deploy the flow for in-container testing. Of course there is
					nothing out-of-the-ordinary here, it's just deploying your WAR file for
					example to a servlet container or application server.</para>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</para>
		<para>
			<emphasis>Note that of course, some of these steps can happen in parallel; coding
			of artifacts such as Action classes can perfectly be done right along with
			implementing your view resources (JSP, Velocity templates, et cetera).</emphasis>
		</para>
	</sect1>
<!-- 	<sect1>
		<title>Designing the flow</title>
		<para>
			The search and master/detail flow for the Phonebook application allows a user
			to:
			
			<numberedlist spacing="compact">
				<listitem>
					<para>Search for a 
-->
</chapter>