<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="overview">
  <title>Overview</title>

  <sect1>
    <title>What is BeanDoc (and why would I care?)</title>

    <para>Spring BeanDoc is a tool for documenting context definition files
    used in <ulink url="http://www.springframework.org">Spring</ulink>
    projects. An unmodified beandoc run produces HTML with a JavaDoc-ish look
    and feel to it, and graphs of the context showing dependencies,
    inheritance and other common constructs. However, the tool is highly
    configurable and extensible to meet most needs.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/main.png" />
      </imageobject>

      <caption><para>Sample output showing a JPetStore page</para></caption>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>The tool documents a multi-file application context in a repeatable,
    fast way and is runnable from standard development tools such as IDE's,
    Ant or command shells. Re-using a standard set of properties tailored to
    your needs with different projects or context files is a trivial
    operation.</para>

    <para>BeanDoc integrates with other open source tools where appropriate.
    Significant among them is the graphing package for generating the image
    graphs, and this will need to be downloaded and installed separately on
    your machine. Fortunately this is an extremely simple operation.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Obtaining BeanDoc</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>CVS</title>

      <para>Spring BeanDoc is part of the SpringFramework CVS repository,
      existing as a separate module from the main Spring sources. You can
      <ulink
      url="http://fisheye1.cenqua.com/browse/springframework/spring-beandoc">view
      the module</ulink> via Fisheye or check it out anonymously using CVS.
      Shown below are the commands required from the CVS command-line, see
      your preferred tool's documentation if you wish to use that
      instead.</para>

      <programlisting>cvs -z3 -d:pserver:anonymous@cvs.sourceforge.net:/cvsroot/springframework co spring-beandoc</programlisting>

      <para>SourceForge has <ulink
      url="http://sourceforge.net/cvs/?group_id=73357">more
      information</ulink> on anonymous CVS access for the springframework
      project.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Releases</title>

      <para>If you don't wish to track CVS you can <ulink
      url="http://opensource.atlassian.com/confluence/spring/display/BDOC/Home">download
      release files</ulink> which contain all of the project sources, samples
      and compiled documentation instead.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Building the sources</title>

      <para>Having checked out or unzipped the project sources, cd to the root
      of the project directory and invoke <literal>ant dist</literal> to
      generate the <literal>spring-beandoc.jar</literal> file. This file,
      along with all other runtime dependencies will be placed in
      <literal>target/dist</literal> (unless you overrode the target directory
      in your local <literal>build.properties</literal>). Runtime libs can now
      be added to any of your Spring projects that you wish to document, or
      just left where they are and referenced on the classpath.</para>

      <sect3>
        <title>Maven</title>

        <para>The project contains configuration for a Maven build which can
        be run from the project root with;</para>

        <programlisting>maven install:jar</programlisting>

        <para>See <ulink
        url="http://www.schuerig.de/michael/java/maven-beandoc-plugin/index.html">Michael
        Schuerig's page</ulink> for information on using BeanDoc as a Maven
        report.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="overview-graphviz">
    <title>GraphViz</title>

    <para>One of the most useful features of BeanDoc is its ability to
    generate configurable graphs of the context files. The actual graphing
    tool used is called GraphViz, and you will need to obtain and install a
    copy for your platform from <ulink url="http://www.graphviz.org">their
    website</ulink>. Thanks to the ATT guys for a great tool.</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>